A Guide to the Papers of Walt Whitman, 1838-1987
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series 1: Literary Manuscripts
  - "Song of Myself," [ca. 1855-1889], AMs, 36 leaves. #3829 (Bowers #22). (Box-folder 1:88)
    - Page 14. You there!, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 12.5 x 20 cm.
      On a section of white wove paper (12.5 x 20 cm.), inscribed and revised in brown ink and pencil. Deleted with a single vertical pencil stroke. A very large number of pinholes cluster towards the bottom-center of the page, indicating that this was the top half of a full leaf, although one or more verses have been removed from the top. The left side is torn, as if the page had been removed from a notebook. This page was apparently inscribed very close to the publication of the 1855 Leaves; with a few revisions it became part of what would eventually be section 40 of Song of Myself. Not in Notes and Fragments. On the verso, in very light brown ink, appear undeleted notes defining and illustrating such verse forms as "hexameters," "dactyl," "Spondee," "Iambus," and "Trochee." These notes represent an incomplete version of notes on a manuscript currently housed at Rutgers University, and printed by Bucke on pp. 162-63 of Notes and Fragments, although the Leaf 14 notes, like the Song of Myself verses on the recto, do not appear in Bucke. (For another version of the Rutgers notes, partially transcribed by Bucke, see Leaf 36 below.) Grier notes that the Rutgers manuscript probably dates to 1856 or afterwards, when Whitman was pursuing a self-education in poetry, suggesting that the verso notes also date to that period.
    - Page 15. And their voices, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 4.5 x 19.5 cm.
      On a section of the type E laid paper (4.5 x 19.5 cm.), inscribed and revised in pencil. A pencil question mark appears above a very faint line linking "valved" and "cornet." These half-prose, half-poetic notes were revised and incorporated in two separate verses of what would become Song of Myself: the eventual verse 597, in section 26 ("I hear...the keyed cornet") and verse 1067 in section 42 ("Ever the vexer's hoot! hoot! till we find where the sly one hides and bring him/ forth..."). Bucke prints these notes on p. 30 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 16. The horizon's edge, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 8.5 x 20 cm.
      On a section of the type E laid paper (8.5 x 20 cm.), inscribed, revised, and deleted (with a single vertical stroke) in pencil. The corners are cropped irregularly. The first line originally read "Odor of the salt marsh, and of the mud and sea-weed[.]" An earlier version of these lines is also associated with proto- Song of Myself verses in Library of Congress Notebook #80 ("And the salt marsh and creek have/ delicious odors..."). The "unearthly laugh of the laughing-gull" reappears in what would eventually become line 763 (section 33) of Song of Myself. Most of the lines on Leaf 16 were incorporated, however (after further revision), into the tenth poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves. As Bradley and Blodgett note, this poem was titled Poem of The Child That Went Forth, and Always Goes Forth, Forever and Forever in the 1856 edition, after which it became number 9 in the 1860 group Leaves of Grass, number 1 of a different Leaves of Grass group in 1867, and, finally, There Was a Child Went Forth in the 1872 edition. The lines appear on p. 48 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 17. Children and maidens - strong men, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 7 x 21 cm.
      On a section of heavily wrinkled, torn, and smudged unruled white laid paper (7 x 21 cm.) reinforced with white wove paper. All four corners are cropped for mounting. Inscribed, without revisions, in pencil. The laid paper was originally the last page of a letter; a few illegible words and part of a signature can be seen dimly through the back of the composite leaf. Whitman wrote his lines on the verso of the page after turning it sideways. Although Whitman did not use the verses word for word, they may have been part of an early draft of the fourth poem in the 1855 edition of Leaves, eventually titled The Sleepers. The lines appear on p. 46 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 18. Full of wickedness, ca. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 15.5 x 8 cm.
      On a section of white wove paper torn down to 15.5 x 8 cm., inscribed and revised on both sides in medium brown ink and also inscribed and deleted, on the recto, in pencil. Features one set of pinholes in the center. The verses on the recto, while not published word-for-word until 1897, seem to represent an early draft of the poem first published as number 13 of the cluster Leaves of Grass in the 1860 Leaves, and eventually titled You Felons on Trial in Courts. (See 2:2:1 under Leaves of Grass [1860] for a much later version of the poem.) Whitman's careful script and verse forms here also resemble the methods of inscription used for the Live Oak, with Moss poems dated by Bowers to the post-1856, pre-1860 period. The undeleted notes on the back are titled Poems and begin with the lines "A cluster, (same style, as of sonnets li[ke]/ as 'Calamus Leaves')/ of poems, verses, thoughts &c, embodying/ religious emotions/ & thoughts." A cartoon hand in the left margin points to the phrase "religious emotions." Whitman's use of the title Calamus Leaves dates these notes to the same pre-1860 period as the deleted verses on the recto, since Calamus-Leaves was what he renamed the cluster Live Oak, with Moss before settling on Calamus for the 1860 edition. A section of the notes below the rest (beginning "spirituality—the unknown,...") is inscribed in verse form. Bucke prints these, along with [Full of wickedness, I...], on p. 39 of Notes and Fragments. The rest of the notes appear on p. 165; related notes appear on 169 and 176.
    - Page 19. From wooded Maine, ca. 1889, 1 leaf, handwritten, 11 x 18 cm.
      On the verso of a letter (11 x 18 cm.) inscribed in light black ink on (wrinkled) white laid paper, embossed with a red design. All four corners are cropped for mounting. Whitman's lines are inscribed and revised in thick pencil. The letter is dated "Aug 14th /89," and asks Whitman to send the unidentified writer a copy of the "latest special edition" of Leaves of Grass. These trial verses became part of A Twilight Song —subtitled, Bradley and Blodgett note, "for unknown buried soldiers, North and South"—which was first published in the May, 1890 Century and then included in the second annex Good-Bye My Fancy in the 1892 "deathbed" edition of Leaves. This draft does not appear in Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 20. I am become the poet of babes and, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 4 x 14.5 cm. pasted to 4.5 x 15 cm.
      On a composite leaf comprising two sections of the type A notebook paper (4 x 14.5 and 4.5 x 15 cm.) pasted together. Three pinholes appear near the foot of the page. Inscribed and revised on both sides in pencil. The verso lines (beginning "I think I could dash the girder of the earth/ away" and "Surely I am out of my head!") are deleted with several pencil strokes. The deleted number 209 (in brown ink) appears in the top right corner of the lower section. After much revision the recto lines, which are related to lines in Library of Congress Notebook #80, seem to have become part of what would be section 44 of Song of Myself. The verso lines represent an early draft of lines eventually incorporated in section 27 of the poem. Bucke transcribes both sets of verses, with additional lines not preserved in these sections, on pp. 34-5 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 21. American air I have breathed, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 4.5 x 18 cm.
      On a small section of the type B wove paper irregularly cropped, torn, and cut down to 4.5 x 18 cm. Several pinholes appear in the center; some smoke damage appears along the right edge. Inscribed and revised in pencil. Below the verses appear the deleted phrase "Echos [sic] of voices" and the undeleted note "? Personality" beneath a faint horizontal line. Bucke prints the lines on p. 13 of Notes and Fragments. Although Whitman did not publish these verses himself, their structure and the type of paper upon which they are inscribed suggest a close relationship with the lines on Leaf 22, which were revised to form part of section 14 of Chants Democratic in the 1860 edition of Leaves, a set of verses eventually transformed into an independent poem under the title Poets to Come.
    - Page 22. Merely what I tell is not to justify me, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 4 x 15 cm.
      On a small section (4 x 15 cm.) of the same type B paper as Leaf 21, with smoke damage in the upper left corner. The corners are cropped slightly for mounting. Two sets of pinholes appear in the center. Inscribed and revised on both sides in pencil. Bucke transcribes both sets of verses on p. 39 of Notes and Fragments. The recto verses were used as noted under Leaf 21, but the lines on the verso (deleted with several vertical and horizontal pencil strokes) seem to have been rejected.
    - Page 23. Can ? make me so exuberant yet so faintish, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 6 x 19.5 cm.
      On a section of the type E laid paper (6 x 19.5 cm.) with all four corners cropped for mounting. Multiple pinholes run up the center of the page. Inscribed and revised on both sides in pencil. The recto verses bear some similarity to what would eventually form section 28 of Song of Myself, while the deleted lines on the verso (beginning "This mouth is pulled by some sexton for his dismalest fee,") represent a fragment of draft lines eventually incorporated in the sixth poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves, a poem permanently retitled Faces in the 1872 edition. Bucke transcribes both sets of verses on p. 37 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 24. To this continent comes the, ca. 1856-1860, 1 leaf, handwritten, 10 x 13 cm. pasted to 5 x 13 cm.
      On a composite leaf consisting of two sections (10 x 13 and 5 x 13 cm.) of light green type D paper used for trial printings(?) of the title page of the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass (see Leaf 25). (The words "Leaves o[f]," printed in a typeface similar to the one used for the 1855 edition, appear in the bottom right corner of the lower section.) All four corners of the top section, and the lower corners of the bottom section, are cropped for mounting. Multiple pinholes appear in each section. Inscribed and revised in black ink. As Bradley and Blodgett note, the lower set of verses seems to be a later draft of the upper set, even though Bucke prints them in reverse order and as separate fragments on p. 32 of Notes and Fragments. These lines foreshadow a number of poems new to the 1860 edition of Leaves, particularly Proto-Leaf (ultimately titled Starting from Paumanok ) and So long!, as well as several of the poems grouped in the cluster Chants Democratic and Native American.
    - Page 25. Ships sail upon the waters, ca. 1856-1860, 1 leaf, handwritten, 15.5 x 14.5 cm.
      On one section of light yellow type D paper torn down to 15.5 x 14.5 cm. (Part of the word "Leaves" appears in the lower right corner of the verso.) The lower left corner is cropped. Multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed in black ink, with revisions in the same ink and one addition in pencil. On the verso, in blue pencil, appears a quickly scrawled note, reading "Drum Taps—City of Ships[,]" which appears to be in Whitman's hand. This may indeed have been a draft of the poem City of Ships, which first appeared in 1865 as part of the independent publication Drum-Taps, but its similarities to the lines on Leaf 24 and lack of references to the Civil War indicate that it was inscribed prior to the publication of the 1860 edition of Leaves. These lines bear a strong resemblance to verses inscribed on Leaf 7 of Premonition as described above (under Leaves of Grass [1860] 1:1:7), verses that formed section 20 of Proto-Leaf in 1860 and, ultimately, part of section 6 of the poem under the title Starting from Paumanok. Printed on p. 30 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 26. You are English, Irish, Scotch, Welsh, ca. 1856-1860, 1 leaf, handwritten, 10 x 15 cm.
      On one section of white wove paper torn and cut down to 10 x 15 cm., inscribed and revised in very thin brown-black ink. Two pinholes appear towards the right margin. The lower corners are cropped. Whitman's use of the word "Libertad" and way of handling the theme of immigration suggest that this might be part of an early draft of the poem eventually known as A Broadway Pageant, first published in the June 27, 1860 issue of the New York Times as The Errand-Bearers. Bucke prints the verses on p. 39 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 27. Remember if you are dying, ca. 1855-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 8 x 15.5 cm.
      On a section of type B wove paper cut down to 8 x 15.5 cm. All four corners are cropped for mounting. Multiple pinholes run up and down the center. Inscribed and corrected (in only one place) on the recto in pencil, and on the verso in light brown ink and pencil. The verso lines (beginning "[sl]ueing,/...[be]nding,/...halt in the shade,") represent a fragment of a polished pre-1855-publication draft—almost a fair copy, but with interesting revisions nonetheless—of lines that would eventually belong in section 13 of Song of Myself. These verses are inscribed along the ruled lines. Whitman cannibalized this leaf at some point after 1855 to jot down the recto verses perpendicular to the ruled lines. These seem to constitute a complete but very early draft of the poem To One Shortly To Die, first published in the 1860 edition of Leaves of Grass in the cluster Messenger Leaves. (For a later draft see Leaf 28, and for an even later version inscribed shortly before the 1860 publication see 2:3:1 in Leaves of Grass [1860].) In the upper right corner of the recto appear the words "note/ last page of 'Ghost-seers'" in Whitman's hand, suggesting that he had considered forming a cluster under this title, never published, in Leaves, perhaps in the 1860 edition. The phrase "Ghost-seers" recalls a statement regarding Emerson in Leaves-Droppings, a section of correspondence and commentary Whitman appended to the 1856 edition of Leaves: "[Emerson] sees the future of truths as our Spirit-seers discern the future of man..." Bucke prints the recto verses on p. 13 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 28. I must not deceive you - you are to die, ca. 1855-1860, 1 leaf, handwritten, 4 x 14.5 cm.
      On a very small section (4 x 14.5 cm.) of the type A notebook paper. Inscribed and revised on the recto in (smudged) brown-black ink. Fragmentary lines on the verso are inscribed, revised, and deleted in pencil. Four pinholes run up from the center of the leaf towards the upper right corner. The verso lines (beginning "[I] and nobody else am the greatest traitor,") represent a later draft than similar verses in Library of Congress Notebook #80 of what would eventually become part of section 28 of Song of Myself. The recto lines were revised to form part of the 1860 poem To One Shortly To Die. (See Leaf 27 for an earlier draft and entry 2:3:1 under Leaves of Grass. [1860] for a later version.) Bucke prints the recto verses on p. 47 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 29. As procreation, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 6 x 18.5 cm.
      On a small section of white laid paper (6 x 18.5 cm.) with all four corners cropped for mounting. Multiple pinholes in center. Inscribed and revised (in one place) in brown ink. A short horizontal line appears beneath the verses, indicating (along with the finished appearance of the lines) that Whitman conceived of this when written as an independent poem. He may have used it, however, in the 1856 Poem of Remembrances for A Girl or A Boy of These States, which, as Bradley and Blodgett note, became the sixth poem in Chants Democratic and Native American in 1860. It was subsequently shortened by several stanzas (1867) and retitled (1872) Think of the Soul before being excluded from Leaves with the publication of the 1881 edition. The verses on Leaf 29 combine the meanings expressed in both the excluded and preserved sections of Think of the Soul. Bucke prints these verses and a related, longer set of verses on p. 27 of Notes and Fragments; the other lines in Bucke were revised and expanded for use in sections 46-51 of the 1860 poem Proto-Leaf, permanently retitled Starting from Paumanok in 1867.
    - Page 30. Of your soul I say truths to harmonize, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 7.5 x 20 cm.
      On a section of the type D proof sheet paper (light yellow) cut and torn irregularly down to 7.5 x 20 cm. (The words "Leaves of" appear on the verso.) Multiple pinholes appear towards the foot of the leaf, indicating—along with the damaging of the words "The gripe" in the last line by cutting and the appearance of the tops of other letters above the lower edge—that this was the upper section of a larger leaf before Whitman decided to make it an independent poem, adding his characteristic period and hyphen combination at the end of the lines to mark its separateness. Inscribed in brown-gray ink, with revisions in the same ink, in pencil, and in a darker brown ink (in that order). Bucke prints the verses on p. 26 of Notes and Fragments with the annotation "Early or middle fifties, never used," but the lines bear a strong resemblance to a section of prose on p. vi of the preface to the 1855 edition of Leaves of Grass. The verses on this leaf may represent a poetic adaptation of that section.
    - Page 31. Who wills with his own brain, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 5 x 16 cm.
      On a small section of what seems to be type D light yellow paper (5 x 16 cm.). All four corners are cropped for mounting. Inscribed and revised in pencil. Bucke transcribes these verses on p. 28 of Notes and Fragments, combining them with other fragments to form a longer poem. They display some similarities to the eleventh untitled poem of the 1855 edition of Leaves, named Lesson Poem in 1856 and finally, beginning with 1871's Passage to India, Who Learns My Lesson Complete?
    - Page 32. Have I, ca. 1856, 1 leaf, handwritten, 9 x 18 cm.
      On the verso of an irregularly cut and cropped proof sheet (9 x 18 cm.) from the 1856 edition of Leaves of Grass. A few pinholes are scattered around the page. The words "Have I" at the beginning are inscribed on a small scrap of the same paper, which Whitman pasted over some deleted words in the upper right corner that cannot be discerned through the paper. Inscribed and extensively revised in pencil, these verses were part of a larger set of lines before Whitman cut away and (apparently) discarded the rest. Although the page number and many words on the left side of the proof have been cut away, the remaining words identify it as p. 188 from the Poem of Many in One, which eventually became By Blue Ontario's Shore. These unused but also undeleted lines may have been intended for that poem or a number of other poems in Leaves. Bucke prints them on p. 30 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 33. The beef, wheat and lumber of Chicago, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 10.5 x 19.5 cm.
      On a section of white laid letter(?) paper (10.5 x 19.5 cm.) folded in two places, perhaps for mailing. All four corners are cropped, and the right margin is cut irregularly. No pinholes. Inscribed in black ink that has bled in several places from contact with water drops. A long horizontal line divides the first set of draft verses from a pair of trial verses beginning "The railroads with their hundreds/ of lines..." Although these poetic notes are difficult to date, they may represent an intermediate stage between the 1855 Preface to Leaves and the 1856 Poem of Many in One (eventually By Blue Ontario's Shore ), which cast many sentences similar to these from the Preface in poetic form. Two editorial errors relating to the leaf should be mentioned: Bucke prints the fragment on p. 169 as a prose passage, and in republishing Bucke's transcription (still in prose form) Grier reports, on p. 1941 of the Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts (vol. 5) that this manuscript has not been found.
    - Page 34. O I must not forget, ca. 1857-1859, 1 leaf, handwritten, 14 x 12 cm.
      On the verso of a section (14 x 12 cm.) cut from a type C tax form. The corners are all cropped for mounting. Inscribed and revised in pencil. Multiple pinholes cluster towards the foot of the leaf, suggesting that one or more verses were cut away and discarded; this is corroborated by the fact that the final word, "gaunt," ends not with a period but with a comma. Whitman's use of the tax form and the strong similarity this fragment bears (as Bradley and Blodgett note) both to the 1856 Poem of the Road (later Song of the Open Road ) and to the 1860 Proto-Leaf (eventually Starting from Paumanok ) indicate that this may have been a revision of the former poem or, as seems more likely, an early draft of Proto-Leaf intended for the 1860 edition of Leaves. To compare this fragment with extant drafts of Proto-Leaf, under its original title Premonition, see leaves 1:1:1-1:1:33 as described under Leaves of Grass (1860) above. Printed on p. 39 of Notes and Fragments.
    - Page 35. Man, before the rage of whose passions, ca. 1855, 1 leaf, handwritten, 8 x 19.5 cm.
      On one section of white wove paper (8 x 19.5 cm.) ruled on both sides, with the upper corners cropped for mounting. Inscribed in green-black ink with no revisions. These verses seem to have been part of a larger set before Whitman decided to make them an independent poem, adding a hyphen at the end of the last line and cutting off the verses below. (The word "nothing" in the last line was partly cut away as well.) Although written in free verse, the rather conventional nature of this poem suggests an early date of inscription. Bucke does not transcribe it.
    - Page 36. Pentameter - in ancient poetry, ca. 1856, 1 leaf, handwritten, 25 x 13 cm.
      On a full leaf of light tan wove paper (25 x 13 cm.) that seems to have been removed from a notebook; the note "Last Page" and the number 5(?) appear at the top of the leaf. The foot of the page—wrinkled, smudged with erased words, and largely worn away—has been reinforced with a strip of light brown wove paper pasted to the verso. Inscribed in pencil, with one minor revision in brown ink. The leaf is divided with horizontal lines into four sections: "Pentameter," "Anapest," "Dithyrambus/ Dithyramb/ Dithyrambic," and "Caesura." Like the contents of the verso of Leaf 14, these notes represent a version of the poetic definitions that appear in a manuscript currently housed at Rutgers University. Bucke prints the final two sections of these notes on p. 163 of Notes and Fragments, leaving the first two sections untranscribed, evidently because they so closely parallel the more complete Rutgers notes (which he prints in full). Grier lists this manuscript, on p. 357 of Notebooks and Unpublished Prose Manuscripts (vol. 1), as "not found."
  - "Song of the Broad-Axe," n.d., Autograph revisions, 12 pp. on 12 l., 20 cm. x 12 cm., #3829 (Bowers #4). (Box-folder 1:89)
    Revision of poem cluster Song of the Broad-Axe. Revisions are made in ink and blue pencil on printed edition of the poem. Walt Whitman apparently used two volumes to tear the leaves from, as every other page is slightly smaller than the rest, revisions are made only on the recto side of each leaf, and verso is crossed out.
  - Song of the Redwood Tree, 1873, 31 leaves, handwritten.